<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[davetcetera]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>site-lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>davetcetera</title><link/></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 04:08:19 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="site-lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 04:08:19 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator/><item><title><![CDATA[discussion-01]]></title><description><![CDATA[A working discussion space for figuring out how the ITHS Curation Committee should approach:
Defining the structure of an ontology for IT historical artifacts, people, and relationships
Translating that ontology into a database architecture
Running the process collaboratively as a group (not just technically)
An ontology for a historical society isn't just a schema. It's a set of claims about what kinds of things exist, how they relate, and what the organization believes is worth tracking. Before touching any database tool, the committee needs to answer questions like:
What is the primary unit of record? (An artifact? A product line? A company? A person? An event?)
What does "historical significance" mean for this organization? (Who decides? By what criteria?)
How do we model influence and lineage? ("X led to Y" is a relationship, but there are many kinds of causality)
What is the boundary between canonical record and user contribution?
These are editorial and philosophical questions, not technical ones. The database follows from the answers.These examples are chosen because they faced the same core challenge: a community needed to agree on what things are before they could build anything.The Getty Research Institute maintains three controlled vocabularies — the Art &amp; Architecture Thesaurus (AAT), the Union List of Artist Names (ULAN), and the Thesaurus of Geographic Names (TGN). These are among the most mature cultural heritage ontologies in existence.Relevance to ITHS:
They separate concept records (what a thing is, abstractly) from instance records (a specific object or person)
ULAN explicitly models relationships between artists: teacher/student, collaborator, influenced-by
The AAT has a formal process for community submissions and editorial review — this maps well to the "canonical vs. user submission" problem
Key lesson: They started with use cases, not with schema. "What questions do curators actually ask?" drove the structure.Reference: <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/" target="_self">getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies</a>Wikidata is a general-purpose, community-maintained knowledge graph that underlies much of Wikipedia's structured data. Everything is a statement about an item, with properties and qualifiers.Relevance to ITHS:
It explicitly handles the "X influenced Y" problem via properties like influenced by, has part, follows, followed by
It has a clean separation between the item (canonical) and references (sourced claims)
It's entirely open and the data model documentation is excellent for learning how to think about these problems
Key lesson: Their data model evolved through community consensus via "WikiProjects" — groups that decided on the properties and structure for a domain (e.g., WikiProject Video Games, WikiProject Computing). This is a direct model for how the ITHS committee could work.<br>Reference: <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Wikidata:WikiProjects" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Wikidata:WikiProjects" target="_self">wikidata.org/wiki/Wikidata:WikiProjects</a>The CHM has an online collection catalog that models hardware, software, people, and corporate history. They've had to solve the same "what is a canonical item?" question — is the canonical item the product design, the specific manufactured unit, or the product line?Relevance to ITHS:
Their distinction between artifact (a physical thing), object type (a class of thing), and lot (a collection) maps onto the ITHS problem of personal submissions vs. canonical records
They use a controlled vocabulary for significance/impact categories
Key lesson: They distinguish "what the object is" from "what the object means" — physical description is separated from historical narrative. This prevents the ontology from collapsing under the weight of interpretation.<br>Reference: <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://computerhistory.org/collections/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://computerhistory.org/collections/" target="_self">computerhistory.org/collections/</a>Rick Prelinger's film archive and the broader Internet Archive have grappled with how to describe media items that have complex provenance chains — one film might be a copy of a copy, with annotations added by multiple hands.Relevance to ITHS:
The "user submits their copy or story of a canonical item" feature is essentially a provenance and versioning problem
Dublin Core and Schema.org (which IA uses heavily) are good prior art for simple, flat metadata that is still interoperable
Key lesson: Don't invent what already exists. Dublin Core, Schema.org, and SKOS cover a huge amount of the basic metadata and relationship vocabulary. Start by mapping your concepts to these before creating custom properties.Open Library models the same three-tier structure that ITHS likely needs:Key lesson: This hierarchy is well-understood and worth adopting directly. It cleanly separates the abstract thing from its instantiations.<br>Reference: <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://openlibrary.org/developers/api" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://openlibrary.org/developers/api" target="_self">openlibrary.org/developers/api</a>Based on the above examples, here is a rough sequence for how the committee might work:Before any data modeling, collect 10–15 concrete questions that the database should be able to answer. Examples:
"What hardware innovations came out of Xerox PARC and what products did they influence?"
"Show me a timeline of storage media from punch cards to SSDs"
"Who were the key engineers at DEC and what did they go on to build?"
"What members have submitted photos of Apple I machines?"
These become the test cases for the ontology. If a proposed schema can't answer them, it's incomplete.Working from the use cases, list the types of things and types of relationships that appear. Don't worry about the database yet. A whiteboard or a simple document is fine.Entity types might include: Person, Organization, Product, ProductLine, Concept/Innovation, Event, Document/Publication, PhysicalArtifact (user submission).Relationship types might include: EmployedBy, InventedBy, InfluencedBy, PrecededBy, PartOf, VersionOf, ContributedTo.Before designing custom schema, check if Schema.org, Wikidata properties, or the Getty AAT already have the concept. This saves time and enables future interoperability.Write entity definitions and relationship definitions in plain sentences before touching any technical notation. Example:
A Product is a commercially released item (hardware or software) with a known manufacturer and release date. A Product may have a PrecededBy relationship to another Product if the earlier Product was a direct technical or commercial predecessor.
Pick one domain (e.g., personal computers from 1975–1985) and build the schema for just that slice. Load a small amount of real data. See what breaks.Only after Phases 1–5 is it worth deciding: relational, graph, or hybrid? Document store? The answer should fall out of the data naturally, not be chosen up front.
What is the minimum viable set of entity types to launch with?
Who has editorial authority over canonical records vs. user submissions?
Is the goal a public-facing database, an internal curatorial tool, or both?
What existing databases (Wikidata, CHM catalog) should we link to rather than duplicate?
How do we handle contested history? (Competing claims of "who invented X") Share this doc with the committee for feedback
Schedule a use-case collection session (Phase 1)
Identify which committee members have worked with any of the reference systems above
Look at the existing Drupal 7 database schema — what entities does it already have?
]]></description><link>projects/iths/curation/discussion-01.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">PROJECTS/ITHS/CURATION/discussion-01.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 04:03:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[WHY THIS]]></title><description><![CDATA[I basically organize everything I do in these buckets called Projects. Home Projects, Fun Projects, Hobby Projects, School Stuff Masquerading As Projects, etc.It's just simpler, and something I adopted while doing software projects - everything is a project that doesn't have a more logical grouping construct (which does exist - Classes, for example). Then I adopted it when doing formal LLM-assist stuff.My ~/projects folder:<img alt="CleanShot 2026-02-15 at 08.08.22.png" src="attachments/cleanshot-2026-02-15-at-08.08.22.png" target="_self">Claudsidian is a concept I made up which is loosely using Obsdian and Claude together in some manner.<br>
My <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://claudsidian.com/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://claudsidian.com/" target="_self">Claudsidian</a> folder :<br><img alt="CleanShot 2026-02-15 at 08.11.33.png" src="attachments/cleanshot-2026-02-15-at-08.11.33.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>projects/why-this.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">PROJECTS/WHY THIS.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 15:16:12 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[20260213 - FRIDAY]]></title><description><![CDATA[
WEB HTML EXPORT for Obsidian investigated
built out full workflow
now have <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://davetcetera.daveccampbell.com/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://davetcetera.daveccampbell.com/" target="_self">this</a> to show for it
<br>more details <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="THIS SITE" data-href="THIS SITE" href="about/this-site.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">here</a> ]]></description><link>logs/20260213-friday.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">LOGS/20260213 - FRIDAY.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 15:09:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[THIS SITE]]></title><description><![CDATA[Even this website is something interesting to talk about - at least to me.For the past 6 months or so I've been fairly enamored with using LLMs to build (mostly) software stuff. I've always enjoyed building things in the world of general internet-related technologies, and for the last half of my professional career I was either building, supporting, or monitoring enterprise tooling and platforms across several industries.I always enjoyed stumbling across a nice batteries-included tutorial to build some cool thing in docker, or some vendors detailed installation for their community-edition or self-hosted option.I, early-on, installed a <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.proxmox.com/en/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.proxmox.com/en/" target="_self">proxmox</a> server in my basement, and used <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.portainer.io/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.portainer.io/" target="_self">portainer</a> to make building platforms and docker-based applications super convenient.But now, using LLMs that are aware, by definition, of how everything is built and how they work, dynamic and mostly right tutorials are at our fingertips for ANYTHING - and simply by asking for it.<br>This site is constructed in <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://obsidian.md/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://obsidian.md/" target="_self">Obsidian</a>, and using an Obsidian <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://obsidian.md/plugins?search=web%20html%20export" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://obsidian.md/plugins?search=web%20html%20export" target="_self">plug-in</a> written, coincidentally, by a fellow I know from <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://engineering.louisville.edu/research/centersinstitutes/larri/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://engineering.louisville.edu/research/centersinstitutes/larri/" target="_self">the lab</a> I am involved with at <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://engineering.louisville.edu/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://engineering.louisville.edu/" target="_self">UofL</a>, <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/KosmosisDire" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/KosmosisDire" target="_self">Nathan George</a>, the Obsidian vault containing these pages can be exported as a complete website.Once the pages are exported locally, a typical static site publishing workflow is used to:
make updates to a repo
push that repo to github
use github pages to 'publish' those pages to a publicly accessible URL
<br>Here is that <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/davecampbell/davetcetera" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/davecampbell/davetcetera" target="_self">repo</a> and <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/davecampbell/davetcetera/blob/main/SETUP-NOTES.md" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://github.com/davecampbell/davetcetera/blob/main/SETUP-NOTES.md" target="_self">here</a> is an explanation / setup page I asked Claude to write for me when I was done.]]></description><link>about/this-site.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">ABOUT/THIS SITE.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 15:06:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[INDEX]]></title><description><![CDATA[You've entered DavEtcetera - which is exactly what you might think that would be. Random-ish things in my world that I decided to write about.A test link:
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://wunderground.com" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://wunderground.com" target="_self">The Weather</a>]]></description><link>index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">INDEX.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 14:30:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[ME]]></title><description><![CDATA[Dave Campbell
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://daveccampbell.com" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://daveccampbell.com" target="_self">website</a>
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.linkedin.com/in/daveccampbell/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/daveccampbell/" target="_self">linked-in</a>
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.facebook.com/daveccampbell" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://www.facebook.com/daveccampbell" target="_self">facebook</a>
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://x.com/daveccampbell" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="https://x.com/daveccampbell" target="_self">X</a>
]]></description><link>about/me.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">ABOUT/ME.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 14:16:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[CleanShot 2026-02-15 at 08.11.33]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="attachments/cleanshot-2026-02-15-at-08.11.33.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>attachments/cleanshot-2026-02-15-at-08.11.33.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">attachments/CleanShot 2026-02-15 at 08.11.33.png</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 13:12:46 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[CleanShot 2026-02-15 at 08.08.22]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="attachments/cleanshot-2026-02-15-at-08.08.22.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>attachments/cleanshot-2026-02-15-at-08.08.22.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">attachments/CleanShot 2026-02-15 at 08.08.22.png</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 13:12:40 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[STAYING BUSY]]></title><description><![CDATA[some things to keep me busy
LLMs
OBSIDIAN STUFF
]]></description><link>items/staying-busy.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">ITEMS/STAYING BUSY.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 15:59:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[HOME]]></title><description><![CDATA[The first page.Where you go to sleep.]]></description><link>home.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">HOME.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 15:56:20 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>